foreign
hello and welcome everyone
this is act INF or extreme number 3.1
it's November 3rd 2022 our guest of
honor is Bijan herzi and we're really
looking forward today to talking about
the free energy principle octave
inference and your experience and recent
work
however for today you've requested that
I set the stage with a little bit of
context on some of the history and
development of the active inference
Institute and by way of doing so set us
up for serendipitous Collision in our
paths centering around applied
organizational active inference and the
free energy principle
so I connected with the co-founders of
the active inference Institute then the
active inference lab which is what it
was called until about June 2022 this
year and we connected after hearing Carl
friston speak with Lex Friedman
and got excited around some of the
opportunities around this developing
framework of active inference and the
free energy principle the potential that
a unifying framework could help us
understand perception cognition and
action across different kinds of complex
and nested systems and then specifically
applying those models in the context of
especially remote teams and
organizations
and that resulted in our 2020 work
active inference and behavior
engineering for teams which additionally
added in some systems engineering
perspectives especially related to
ontology life cycle perspective
continuous delivery continuous
integration and so on
also drawing from an open science in an
open source background and since then
we've been on a journey
we've been learning and applying active
inference and our structure has
developed
today where the active inference
Institute and we're working on some
novel formalizations of our
organizational structure and all these
other important aspects of successful
which is to say surviving organizations
and organisms and that's what led us to
find your work
and immediately resonate with it as some
of the finest contemporary examples of
experience guided and shaped and
situation tested cases of organizational
active inference so that is how we came
to be excited about this area and use
the terms every day and use the ideas
and their relationships in our strategy
and to come across your work and see it
as salient
good thank you Daniel well first of all
thank you very much for inviting me on
this live uh chat I've been obviously
familiar with the active inference
Institute
um I think it was through the
theoretical neurobiology group of fruits
and that I got signed up to your
newsletter and I was really intrigued by
um really the diversity of activities of
media products you're generating in
order to advance the case actually for
the active inference framework
uh when you when you want to ask
actually is there any support uh uh from
a governance point of view uh that's
really when we started actually engaging
because I always feel that
um in the area in particular not for
profit I like to pay my debts and
support it now I do think that actually
you're doing an incredible job it's uh
clearly still at a very early stage
which is actually equally true for the
active interference movement
um uh in in the respective Sciences so
um maybe for for those who are in the
audience not too familiar actually with
what really active inference
um is about it's it's it's really very
philosophical and very scientific at the
same time actually there's a
mathematical framework underlying it
which has been applied actually in
machine learning uh and actually in Carl
Kristen's work which is the neural
Imaging work so
um it is not just just a philosophical
concept but it is actually
something which has been applied in hard
science and based on mathematical
formulas but when you when you really
move away from the from the mathematical
model and you move more to a
philosophical model then actually a much
more General audience starts
understanding that actually active
inference is maybe the only way to
engage with the world which is
increasingly discontinuous and very
distributed and I will briefly just say
my own path of how I came across
actually into the concept and then maybe
a more General audience Beyond actually
Neuroscience machine learning and
biology will start understanding how
relevant the concept of active inference
is of how you build actually your own
worldwide model to navigate and in the
world of business where I'm from how to
actually
allocate resources in very
I call it discontinuous environments I
don't like the word uncertainty because
uncertainty is a very subjective concept
and anyone saying that the world is
uncertain is more reflection and
admission of the very limitations of the
world model they have and that's really
where active interference comes in so my
view and my origin actually of of
engaging with the active inference
concept came through looking at
corporate governance looking at the
challenges actually boards leading
organization type in engaging with the
world which is
as they say very difficult to predict
and we look at an inferential model and
when you look specifically at the Active
interference model you start looking at
a system which is actually a wonderful
system to look at and all of a sudden
you can break actually a world which
seems to be
quite difficult to predict into
something you can navigate actually in a
wonderfully simple way and the way I
look at it is really at the following
six components and uh I deliberately did
not prepare presentation a because I'm
very bad with presentations uh to
prepare them in the first place but I do
understand for the audience sometimes
it's much easier to have it visualized
in front of you so I'm trying really in
simple ways to visualize for you in your
head and you may close your eyes as you
do this or how you build the active
inference framework really bottom up in
a very simplistic way
effectively there's really two things
one has to always look at when you look
at the world there's things you know and
there's things you don't know
the second dimension is there are things
you control and there are other things
you don't control
and this is this is a fact there's many
things we don't know this is the unknown
which is outside
and sometimes inside even and there's
many things which are beyond our control
and now we have to build bottom-up a
model which allows us actually to
navigate through this and the way the
active inference model is built is that
you're looking at four states and I will
go into the states in a second
you look at actually a wall or a blanket
which is actually separating the known
from the unknown which is really the
inner World from the outer world
and you have a very simple first order
principle which has no purpose in its
own right other than orchestrating this
whole thing and orchestrating means we
have only one one objective we are
pursuing and effectively
in social life you can actually bring
down
our ultimate objective as we navigate
and we deal with uncertainty or
unpredictability is we want to minimize
surprise and minimize surprise
mathematically it's really a matter of
minimizing
the error of probability estimates and
I'm coming now to the states we have an
active state which is really our our
actions
our actions actually determine our
sensory state which is what we sense we
have an outer world the external State
and we have an inner State the
interstate is really our resources in
The Firm context you may see actually
what are the firm resources now you look
at these four states active sensory
internal and external very simple
and the internal and the external are
really related through a wall which we
call the Markov blanket and the Markov
blanket does really manage of how we try
and minimize our probability estimates
to constantly updating our beliefs so
and we do this by Trying to minimize at
every juncture in a very generative way
free energy free energy and information
theory is really just a measure of error
so once you see this you see in a very
very simple way to distill this model
now that actually you need to act
to create your own Sensations which
allow you to actually continuously
update your beliefs what beliefs you
have about actually the unknown world
and this is a very generative model the
generative model itself doesn't encode
anything but the general generative
model is just putting into a very
Dynamic relationship how these four
states are being governed
and this is really kind of the theory
part of it when you look at it from a
material and from a practical point of
view you can very quickly see for a firm
that actually there shouldn't be any
uncertainty what you need is you need to
engage in a very active way with the
world with a very clearly defined
prediction model which generates
predictions and your actions
continuously actually update those
predictions and eventually you will
minimize actually the error so what that
means concrete what does it mean
precisely in the context of strategy
when you look in organizations and
that's obviously the field where I have
a lot of experience as a as a board
member as a CEO
traditionally
the strategy process and this is how
they teach it at management schools is
very environment driven the objective is
to say you've got to analyze the
environment in order to Define what your
strategy is
and the active interference view is that
this is wrong actually your strategy is
really interpretation driven which is
effectively by your predictions it's
driven and then you look for the data
points in the environment to either
confirm refute fine-tune actually your
predictions and eventually if you're not
right with your predictions you've got
to update your prediction model so what
does that mean precisely when you look
now at strategy there's only one thing
as a hyper prior working in Bayesian
terms
there's only one thing which is import
and that's what's your purpose what's
the purpose of the company and if the
purpose of the company is clear
the top which is the board the executive
leadership start generating prediction
models of how to best realize this
purpose
and then it's really for the rest of the
organization in a very iterative model
to feedback button up the data points
and then actually it becomes a very
continuous process hence the title of my
book is also continuous transformation
it's a process which is is is is is is
is becoming integral to the DNA of
actually being being in the game
competing in the marketplace
strategy is no longer about top-down
content prescriptions it's really a
top-down bottom-up continuous
interactive generative process so if you
look at it active inference
is
normatively speaking really of course
the theory but it really is a process
model it's a process model of how to
minimize surprise and uncertainty in a
very complex world and when you look at
biological systems they have done this
in wonderful
wonderfully self-organizing mechanisms
and I think the challenge for the
business world is to reintroduce and
bring to life actually self-organizing
mechanisms and the active inference
framework is such a framework and when
you look at my work in Business
Administration I have adapted the active
inference framework to how to make it
work and what it means in the context of
business organizations
wow there's a lot there
active inference as a process model for
minimizing uncertainty in complex worlds
and a broader theme of using Cutting
Edge developments in as evidenced by
your books bibliography everything from
cognitive science of individuals to
organizational studies and quantum
mechanics all these interesting areas
and also really awesome how you framed
some of the zeroth principles or the
commitments that this first principles
framework makes like the separation
between things you know and things you
don't know things you control and things
you don't control and of course all the
nuancing that can happen like a
Continuum of controllability
so I guess to put it back into the
embodied Court what do these top-down
expectations and bottom-up signals look
like are those emails or what are those
actual operational details of this type
of organizational design
well first of all
um
base
um it's a very good question because
it's a it's a it's kind of funny also
when I did the empirical work supporting
actually my theoretical work
um it's really funny how companies
try to make the case that they operate
actually in this way now obviously in
today's world you have many technology
technology-based tools which allow
companies
um to engage in very distributed
environments in real time slack for
example is one of those where you create
actually
you connect actually pop down button and
you engage it to the bottom in a in a in
a very interesting way
um as part of my dissertation and and
and and the book research
I went into the question you asked right
now a little bit deeper and starting to
understand
how companies in an age where there's
many
technology tools for massive engagement
of how they can use actually the bottom
in order to refine their top-down
predictions
um when you look at
the early days it was kind of all about
collective intelligence
um Collective collaboration how you
bring sometimes it was more on a project
level
at IMD in lausanne and there's two
researchers they have created actually a
massive intelligence
undertaking which was really meant
to be able
to define the questions in the first
place which actually the base should
respond to so what are the relevant
questions because obviously by asking
what are they question refrain something
and you frame the past how can you even
neutralize this by empowering the base
to generate actually what are the right
questions to do
um there is a big well I I shouldn't say
there is a big movement but there has
been a movement and there has been a lot
of research on it and actually they're
very big companies from Red Bull to
Daimler Benz to many big companies which
have applied it which is called open
strategy and the idea of the open
strategy framework was that actually
the Strategic issues which are relevant
for the company to compete in the long
term should be generated through the
base the employee base of the company
and they were obviously various
technology tools which were deployed in
order to do this
I think all these things have very mixed
results
because the question is can you really
open to such a big uh Forum uh sensitive
strategy questions
um so it has been controversial within
the respective companies some companies
had really some good input but on the
other hand it raises also expectations
in the employee base and if it's too
project driven rather than actually
really integral to the DNA on a
continuous basis usually these things
and they fail one idea
um I like a lot having said this I must
admit I haven't implemented it in my own
companies I like the idea when you think
in a company the very top is the board
of directors and you could see beneath
it obviously the executive leadership
team I like very much the idea of
creating Shadow boards
with younger employees and who face the
same agenda the top board is facing and
you look at what kind of discussion
points what kind of agenda items what
kind of action recommendations come from
the base and I think if you do this in a
structured way it's a great way of
incentivizing actually the high
potential in the company but also I
think what you're doing is actually you
really engage the base to think
strategically and to challenge the top
with exactly the very same topics
they're facing and by the way that may
generate actually future agenda points
as well so I think
the idea has to be definitely to open up
there's no question about it
um but probably to do it in a more
focused way that's where I think it's
the shadow board is is a really great
thing I I just
um communicated on this on LinkedIn this
week
but
I think what is much more important
and this is what the active inference
framework and that's why I believe the
active inference Institute is doing an
invaluable job
by starting to understand actually what
active inference and practical
application really means we have to
change fundamentally the way we
communicate and the biggest problem you
have in organizations any organization
is the communication
and whenever I look at the top down
bottom-up Bayesian brain
you obviously understand that an
organization will never ever be able to
work that efficiently connecting the top
and the bottom nervous system in a way
to operate
but we have to approximate it and all of
a sudden when you start understanding
the Bayesian brain in your science
and you apply the active inference
framework
to social organism
man-made artifacts
you all of a sudden start understanding
how much friction there is and myself as
a business leader CEO chairman
I am only dedicated to one thing and
from there everything flows brilliantly
and I think this is the essence of great
and future oriented leadership in this
continuous Market environments is take
the friction out between the bottom and
the top and there's far too much
friction in all the organizations and
that leads many times to the fact that
you have very valuable intelligence all
the intelligence in an organization is
at the very bottom there is no
intelligence at the top
and the top is only as intelligent as
the bottomless so a very key and almost
categoric imperative
for firm performance for a company's
performance and competitiveness
is really how do you bring the bottom-up
intelligence all the way up and only on
that basis will you develop smart
prediction models great predictions and
bring them back to the bottom to
challenge them and evolve them it's a
generative process so I think what we
need to finally say goodbye to and this
is the key message of the active
inference framework we need to say
goodbye that you can drive
competitiveness a future strategy by
content prescriptions
put it in the right process they find a
very clear purpose
and follow A first order principle to
orchestrate everything which is free
energy minimization as I said before in
information theoretical terms free
energy is nothing but a measure of error
so all we want to do is measure the
error between our predictions and the
present States we notice and once you
follow that process you set free an
organization I gave an example in my
book which is about actually when you do
the budget and right now again in
October November is the budgeting period
for companies to set the budget for the
next year again you're facing loans and
unknowns you're facing issues you
control there's other issues you don't
control and the management team is
challenged to put a budget together the
only way they can
Neil was the unknown is by defining
actions they believe can generate the
right stimuli
to actually update their prediction
models in a continuous way so when I
look at the budget
of course I have to look at the numbers
but I'm really not interested in the
numbers I'm looking at the underlying
assumptions and the hypotheses
and I'm looking at the action model and
the precise actions the management team
looking to undertake to optimize
actually their predictions and to gain
more and more control and to turn the
unknown into the known and that's all it
is about as we navigate through this
world be more in control
no more and have less of the unknown and
that's a continuous process and I think
if anyone gets it and gets the active
inferior framework
then I think
we will no longer talk about
uncertainty in business in the way we
talk about it today we are really
talking more about model uncertainty but
there is no such thing as uncertainty in
an objective way
lot two
add there but really interesting how you
highlighted the necessity of
appropriate Communications and pointed
to Communications as one of the biggest
areas of Challenge and uncoincidentally
also one of the areas for which for
digital organizations the affordances
are entirely stated
and the wiring diagram of the
organization so to speak the effective
and the functional causal edges to use
some analogies from neuroimaging those
edges are composable often digitally and
increasingly with augmented and digital
collaborators and so that space of
wiring is vast
it's faster than building a physical
building or object because it can exist
with many different counterfactuals and
in kind of imagined spaces so how do we
go from this insight and maybe even some
imperatives or heuristics like to reduce
the friction between the bottom and the
top as you described towards a given or
particular organizational structure in a
certain context
there have been uh models I think one
company Zappos uh has been doing this uh
more in a holographic way trying to
really
um
um uh
the way I say it in very simplistic
terms looking at organizational models
and organizational forms
if we do agree as a working assumption
that the world is discontinuous and
distributed then I do believe that
organizational structures need to be
much more distributed and much less
centralized and I think we need to break
up companies and bring them into smaller
units
and Empower them and they will be much
more performing because what we're doing
is we're
minimizing or optimizing in a certain
way the pathway between bottom-up
intelligence and and stimuli going
actually to top-down predictions and
that should be the ultimate objective
how can we minimize the friction and
sometimes the friction is really a
function of how we simplify organization
and forms of organizing what's very
interesting when you look
there is kind of and it comes really
from prehistoric times before even
language appeared when actually people
communicated in forms of touching each
other
that the maximum number of a community
is 150
that's where you can distinguish with
touches in in certain ways and that's
kind of a magic number which has been
actually I guess these are the very
Origins at as some researchers in the in
the language field have informed me but
I think
um it's funny to see that there's a
number of companies which look at the
150 to 200 as the magic number and
that's when actually an organizational
entity should be no bigger and if a
company has 50 000 employees then it
should be really in much smaller units
and Empower them and I think
um that's what I'm doing my company's
office you're not that big but in my
company I have four companies
um which are quite distinct companies
but I think that's the strengths because
they form one Unity but they remain very
very distinct and I can see that they
are much more performing if they were
just business units as part of a bigger
thing so there they have very autonomous
and very respective leadership
structures and I do believe
um to your point looking at the form of
organization uh is very critical and I
do think having said so there have been
many researchers before who have been
looking at Neuroscience the structure of
the brain transfer showing it actually
to organizational science and it has
been certainly true for biology but I'm
always fascinated looking into biology
how
our
first of all how perception
is very Spacey specific
and how we have a tendency to generalize
and obviously make it very human-centric
the world
and once we get to the point that we
start understanding that the world is
not human-centric
then actually I think we will be much
more open to be enriched by the insights
and the inspiration the biological world
can give us and to actually become aware
of the very limitations we have and how
we can actually navigate with
uncertainty
and there the active appearance
framework will come in and I think the
problem we have as a human specie is
that we are the only specie which has
this outstanding power of learning
but we have so many limitations which
are very severe and
kind of we're empowered on the one side
was learning but we are completely
handicapped on the other side we can't
see electromagnetic waves so there's
many interesting uh theories
um uh and some of them I I really like
that our objective or if you look at the
very sense of evolution
has never been about seeing the truth as
it is
our existence and our
epistemic for Raging and exploration is
not about approximating truths actually
most of the time we do ignore the truth
it's all about Fitness payoffs because
we want to survive
and we want to procreate and it's all
about that and that drives our behavior
and you start not looking at things the
way they are as much as actually our
engagement you see we see a desktop but
behind the test Hub are pixels in in
many different things which actually
create our perception but what we're
seeing is definitely not the truth so I
think unless we get to the point where
we say goodbye to this very classical
notion and that's why I bring also my
book the relation and the juxtaposition
between classical physics and quantum
physics we have to move to quantum
physics and we need to actually start
understanding the world does not operate
according to classical laws it really
operates according to Quantum law and
once you start doing it
I think you have to
embrace
our existence but the way we control not
control the known and the unknown in a
completely new way and my contribution
in the active inference framework is
really to say this is something which is
immensely valuable to redefining what
strategy means in the business world I
know we're at the very beginning that's
why I'm sure the audience engaging with
us today is a very small audience
but I'm and I have to say as you could
see also with my theoretical
introduction to the active inference
framework it is so abstract for many
people for us it's so natural and we see
the mathematical formulas behind it and
we see the consistency
but
forming a book writing a book even for
the business Community makes it almost a
book nobody can read and nobody can
understand
but I'm absolute view of the conviction
that this book that the work of the
active inference Institute and Kyle
friston has been our great source of
inspiration for all of this is setting
free a movement and I'm absolutely
convinced it's just a matter of time
that this become in a very significant
way mainstream
wow well a lot to add there the
recurrent mention of the distributed
systems and strategy in distributed
systems reminds me of my earlier
graduate school work on foraging
decision making in ants where no single
Nest mate knows how many seeds The
Colony has how many seeds there are out
there what's the humidity what's the
water loss rate none of the relevant
information and yet it embodies through
Behavior development Evolution ecology
it embodies a solution to the
regularities of that Niche which
includes like abiotic challenges and
biotic challenges and then you connected
to epistemic foraging which is what we
use to describe when actions are
undertaken with the imperative primarily
of reducing uncertainty and gaining
information
and the free energy imperative has a
dual epistemic and pragmatic component
so under conditions of high certainty
epistemically the pragmatic component
can be dialed in in the special case
converging on utility learning and then
in scenarios with a flatter landscape
where there's less of a sharpness or a
need for pragmatism there's an
exploratory landscape where the
epistemic value in the novelty can be
generated and so there's just so much
there in thinking about distributed
systems in biology and in organizations
which after all are biological too so
what are your closing thoughts
no I think we
um uh we covered certainly for an
audience to get an Insight of active
interference framework uh applying it I
like very much your last contribution
because I'm fascinated by the work you
have done with the ants and even the
brains of ants I mean you you're going
down to a level which is almost a
Quantum in a certain way
um
and uh I uh I I I I can only eat
reiterate that I
really would love to see and hence this
interview is my contribution also of
really firmly establishing the active
inference Institute as a great force for
a whole new way of being inspired by
biology Neuroscience
um to embrace the world
with a completely different mindset and
I think the world is today in a state
where
it's so obvious
that actually we are overwhelmed whether
it's from a geopolitical point of view
whether it's from a from a from an
economic point of view and eventually
from a psychological point of view
because the Dynamics have become very
complex why because technology has
empowered every person to have actually
a Beyond imaginable impact on the whole
one individual potentially to be I don't
like the word disruptive but to generate
discontinuities and that makes it
actually increasingly difficult to
construct an algorithm with not only
what variables are part of it but how do
the variables relate and what is their
respective weighting in in in the
algorithm to start developing actually a
way moving forward and I am of the
conviction and I see it reading the
mainstream newspapers
I don't really reading newspapers but
looking at actually uh through the
voices which come through from the
leaders in various forums
they are overwhelmed and they have
reached the very limitations
of defining
articulating communicating they're very
World model I think actually they
haven't got a world model any longer and
because they haven't got it they are
confronted with uncertainty and
unpredictability and I do believe that
the time is so ripe for actually
bringing more awareness to the fact of
how we have to work on our models
World models reality models whatever you
want to call it
and more importantly what processes
should be in place
to actually update those models and make
them better and better going forward and
I can start and I have to say they're
wonderful examples which have really and
I want to give this as a closing remark
as an example when you look at the
gaming world I'm obviously coming from
the gaming world as an entrepreneur
you have traditionally reward functions
in a game so let's take a very simple
shoot again
in a shooting game the agent is rewarded
who shoots most of the planes and
eventually is the winner let's assume
that's the logic of the game
when you look at the free energy
minimization powered agent
he has or she has no clue about what the
reward function of the game is zero all
the agent does this the agent starts
playing the game and his only one first
order principle which is to minimize
surprise So eventually the agent starts
learning in order to survive which is
the hyper prior
you need to behave in a certain way in
order not to get shot and you have to
engage in certain behavioral traits
so now you have two agents in one game
the game is a shooter game
there's a reward function powered agent
and there is a free energy
oh
surprise minimization powered agent
the free energy agent will always win
always
because it takes a little bit longer to
train it
but eventually it's you don't need to
know the reward function and the reward
functions are outdated by the time you
communicate them and companies need to
understand this liberalize yourself Free
Yourself actually from all that friction
you're creating with PowerPoint
presentations with top-down
Communications which fossilize
the mindset and the intelligence which
is at the bottom of the company just put
a self-organizing process governed by
the free energy principle in place
and once you have a clearly defined
purpose which is timeless
you create your prediction models and
the journey can start and you will see
there's no more any such thing as
uncertainty it's only a way of how
uncertainty minimizing your models are
and that's the only thing
amazing well
for those who are listening all the way
we expect and prefer that you will get
involved or otherwise allocate your
regime of attention to active inference
and active inference Institute and
hopefully participate in some way
thanks for this
awesome conversation we really
have so much to learn from each other
and from our niche and from the unknown
unknowns and from the bottom and from
all arounds so
awesome and until next time thank you
thank you Daniel much appreciated